It's been a great change to
what I'm used to in Zimbabwe.
When you say, I want to buy a bed, you buy a bed that
is completely already assembled with a mattress.
But I was shocked to find out
the bed comes in a box and,
you have to, like, assemble everything.
I had to buy a drill.
I now have a screwdriver, and I have a hammer.
We don't have to mention the name, but
if we see, let's say, like, Swedish furniture,
we know you have to assemble it yourself.
You're just learning, and already you're contributing
back to the community, you're leading.
the Django Girls, you know,
I felt like a beginner.
I couldn't understand, like, most of
the things they were talking about.
I couldn't understand things that are
going on at DjangoCon
We traveled, like, 33 hours by road to get there.
There were other women who were,
like, almost my age or younger.
Then there were mature women who
were, like, older than me, almost.
Almost like the same age as my
mother, you know, who were learning to. Yeah.
Who were Learning.
Python and Django through
a Django Girls workshop.
I was surprised when I walked into the room
for the first time and I could count the
women who were there at the event.
And that's when I realized what Django Girls
means to the tech community globally, not just
for me as a Zimbabwean in Zimbabwe.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Anna Makarudze.
I'm the fundraising coordinator for Django Girls.
I'm excited to be here at PyPodcats.
So I'll be talking about my work with
Django Girls foundation, as well as my journey
and my work within the community.