Do you also have a special affinity towards dinosaurs?
Actually I am very scared of
dinosaurs I refused to watch
dinosaur movies it scares me a lot
I started learning how to code around the
time I graduated from kinder I was maybe around five years old
Being young also makes it easier for me
to talk to kids I guess especially when I
teach workshops and when I hold hackathons
I guess it helps me relate to them more and
come up with activities that they would
find fun    Being young is
kind of inspires them if I can do all of
these things then so can they I guess
when people have mental health concerns it's
always really challenging to try and reach out
to the appropriate support and so with TEDDY I hope to
make it so that it's easier for counselors
to figure out which students to reach out and to help
Instead of using a computer to write their code
Each student is given a piece of paper where they
can write down their program basically and then
after that the teacher will just scan it and upload it
onto one computer and
run it and that way students will be able
to see it come to life on the digital
screens it's not the case that you need
like 40 computers for one classroom you
actually only need one you're making it
more accessible through public schools and
rural communities
Hello everyone my name is
Mona Obedoza I am a tenth grader and I'm
calling in from the Philippines I'm really
passionate about coding and I advocate
teaching kids how to code at an early age
and to this end I'm also a student
ambassador for Women in AI. I'm the co-leader of
the Girls can Code club at my school and
I'm the founder of the Purposeful Mochii
a local organization that hosts hackathons
and workshops for kids to get started
with coding