um
how do I say this
hello everybody
welcome back to another episode of  PyPodcats
The Hidden Figures of Podcast
we need to cut this
how did you get started into this community
so when I started my PhD
I joined the security lab
so at the beginning
I was actually doing like cryptography
things not related to open source at all
during the day I was working in security
and during the night I was working in open source
and I thought that wasn't cool
I want to be able to help maintainers
like bug bounties or
like the hacky things
but
helping maintainers
implement those best practices in their projects
I always like have this image of like
oh security is super cool like
you know just like what you said
bounty and stuff just look like
like Wild West
like instead of cowboy
you have all these like Sci-Fi heros
and I'm totally not
a very secure person
I jaywalk all the time you know
AI is it good or bad for security in open source
oh my God
I think AI for everything
it should be used very carefully
and I think understanding what AI is
is part of that it's like understanding that
it's not like a magician that's telling you answers
it's just statistics
I've also seen you singing on stage for SciPy
I actually started singing when I was very
very little when I was like
12 years old I went to The X Factor in Colombia
ooo wow
I passed a few rounds then they kicked me out
when I was a kid I wanted to be Shakira
is everybody in Colombia so talented
I mean like I think so
we're cool nerds I love it
yes
hi everyone my name is Juanita
I am a PhD student at UC Santa Cruz
working in open source research and I've
also done a lot of work in community for open source
Scientific Python
if you want to learn more about some of this work
that I've done and my journey in open source
come watch this episode