We should talk more about Mojdeh today.
We are now five organizers.
My close friends call me Moj and my full name is Mojdeh.
I am really happy to be part
of PyPodcats team this year.
So I was fortunate enough to get a
scholarship and this scholarship I think still exists.
It's called Erasmus Mundus Scholarship.
I knew about Erasmus as the Erasmus parties,
so there were a lot of parties.
Currently I'm working as a data
scientist project manager in Saint-Gobain.
It's not really clear what does
Python have to do with glass?
I'm really looking.
Through my window right now.
I don't see any Python code.
No one knows everything.
You have all the language models.
You don't need to know everything anymore.
Yeah, exactly.
It is important that even if you hear it from
LLM or read it from LLM, you question it.
Is there any episode that you particularly
like from last year from the PyPodcats?
I mean the episode that stays a lot
in my mind is the one with Vicky.
I also like the one that Real Python
Joanna.
For me, I didn't know her before the
podcast and I was like, whoa, really?
I get to know a new person. That was. Yeah, that was.
Really nice.
This session to introduce Mojdeh and tell you about last year
a little bit, but very a little bit and also a
little bit more about the outlook for next year.