Because I learned Django
and I felt so empowered.
I was, I can do anything now.
I use Python to write
hardware bindings, which was
for music instruments.
Then I transitioned to doing
machine learning and NLP.
Python is very versatile.
Django was, wow, these kind
of frameworks in 2012,
2013, I was like, I can
build any website I want.
I think there's nothing that
fulfills me more than a room
of people and seeing them glow
by the end because they've
made a PR.
PyLadies
The PyLadies.
This is one of the people, the first
people that show their welcome
and I really appreciate it.
I don't think I would have
moved if they did not
were so welcoming to me.
It's archived now on GitHub, our
repository from then, but you can go
and still see the type of commits
and PRs that we did in the past.
They're not what I would do
now, but I am not embarrassed.
From my
beginnings.
Somewhere,
somehow in one of my polytechnic
days we have basic Computer
Science and I learned C
there. And I un-seen it now.
Hi, my name is Tamara.
I'm an Open Source Software
Engineer at Probabl.
I'm an open source contributor
and maintainer and a, computational
linguistics researcher.
See you in the next
episode of PyPodcast.