People.
It's the people of Python community who give
you that warmth.
We connected that Raspberry Pi prototype
which helped in monitoring the power
fluctuations or power cuts in a particular
building in my college.
Whenever I am sad, I am not happy
working professionally with my job or any
stress I have. It's always the women in this
community that I reach out to.
Python meetups and conferences are I think
they are my savior.
While dealing that stress immediately,
mMy gateway is come to any meet up
immediately.
I keep searching is there any meet up.
Open source detoxing?
I have brother and my brother is a special child.
He is autistic but I dont know how can I
help them.
Are there any communities that are helping?
And then I came to Python community.
This is what I observed being in Python
community is that
how well people with disabilities or mental
disabilities, physical disabilities are
doing wonders.
This encouraged me a lot and also was one
of the aspects that I always wanted to
emotionally get connected
and give my best.
Hello everyone, I am Niharika from India.
I am a developer at Accenture India.
I am working as an application developer
and on meantime other than job I love
contributing to Python community and other
open source communities.
I am really excited to be joining on this
episode of PyPodcats, but I am really
excited to be sharing my experiences in
this episode with fun filled and also with
a lot of learning.