uh
I forgot how we start
Okay Hi everybody and welcome to the PyPodcast
Hidden Figures in Python figure
we are continuing with our scissor see
Hi everybody and welcome to the PyPodcast
so yeah today's guest err today's host
oh my God this is a blooper
like wrangling volunteers is hard
there's a lot of just like management challenges
a lot of the time when people think of Africa
they think of it as like
just like a blob and everything's the same
and it's really not like
there are very big cultural differences
between different African countries
when did you get started with Python?
so I got started um when I was in university
I was coding for food I needed money and um
so I was just taking on these odd jobs
you read a programming book
do you still read programming books
I read a book on PHP once for a job
um
I did read the kubernetes book
I've always been teaching
when I was a little kid
I used to teach grown ups Excel skills
helping people with their homework
was a good source of connection
you did that for free I got paid
if you think about like the business of education
there's there's like so much stuff that you need to do
that isn't teaching
if you have to choose right
you can either work with Python
the programming language or people what would
you choose so I love Python so much
but I think actually people
if you wanna build something big
it's a it's a team sport
people are getting to a point where
we're realizing what the uniquely human skills are
a metaphor I really like is soccer um
your individual skills as a soccer player really matter
quite a lot
a lot of emphasis is placed on passing the ball really
really well
hello everyone I'm Sheena um
watch me on PyPodcasts
we're gonna be talking about PyCon Africa
I'm based in South Africa and it's in my hometown
and we'll also be talking about teaching Python
and teaching teamwork
now break cut hmm