I have to find a job.
Funniest  part was the first screening calls.
You get really weird questions.
That's like what is the expected salary
range? Why do you need so much money?
I think I tried almost all.
I was only mentioning that I didn't try PhD yet.
Working for myself, working for someone
else, starting my own company, growing my
own company, selling my own company.
My first job in the Netherlands was an
executive director.
You working with people online.
People were surprised to know that I'm
female.
Somehow they were expecting just, you know,
another guy like who are you? I was like,
I'm
your engineer, you know,
I was working with self driving trucks.
And after that I jump on getting back to
more like maritime industry and I switched
to working with aircrafts.
How much food should we put in it? How much water,
how much fuel? I have heard in my previous
job that a lot of air traffic planning is
using Prolog.
Is that true when the aircraft is flying
the ATC just passing it from one chunk of
cubes to another chunk of cubes
I'm Una from PyLadies Amsterdam and if
you're interested to learn what is the
connection between cubes in the air
sensor fusion and
going from nothing to something then listen
to this PyPodcats