yeah
hello everybody
welcome back to another episode of PyPodcats
The Hidden Figures of Python
hi everyone
we are PyPodcats
and we are doing this Hidden Figures of Python
because we want to bring more beautiful
and wonderful people to your
notice that you know
that our community doesn't just start from nothing
we have beautiful and wonderful people building them
so here we are
and today we have our wonderful Juanita with us welcome
welcome Juanita
Thank you I'm so excited to be here
do you want to introduce yourself
tell us what you do
so yeah
yeah so I am currently a PhD student at UC Santa Cruz
a lot of the research that I do is actually
related to open source
specifically security
that's kind of what I've been up to lately
but I've been also
kind of like as a side thing in like my volunteer time
I've also
spent a lot of my time with the Scientific Python
Community
one of the community managers
for the Scientific Python Project
which
project that is trying to coordinate
the scientific Python ecosystem
so we do summits we are writing some specs
developing tools and yeah
I'm helping with like a lot of the community
stuff going on
sounds amazing
I guess you're one of these people who send
Python to Mars right ha ha
ha ha
hopefully ha ha
so I'm actually not in the scientific community
um I always
I'm mostly in the web based development using Python
so it's always amazing because I know there is a huge
huge community in the scientific
you know Python
can you tell us more about it
like how did you get started into this community
so it actually goes all the way back to maybe
5, 6 years ago
I started as a as a developer for Spyder
the IDE for Python
which I think it's actually an IDE that is um
meant for scientists not necessarily server developers
but
it's meant to make your development with Python easier
I joined the Spyder team a very long time ago
haha and a lot of the work that I did was actually
focused on documentation and community outreach
I started doing events
I guess um
I I had this like Spyder cast
which I guess is kind of similar to what we're doing
today um
where I kind of invited developers on stage
where they only talked about
um some of the work that they did for Spyder
and I also started to do tutorials and
for Spyder
I guess
I guess it's a way to reach out
more people in the community
But also with this idea of
kind of
turning documentation into something more millennial
like reaching younger generations
um and
and the two people who started this Scientific
Python project which were uh
were Stéfan J. van der Walt and Jarrod Millman
they saw some of my work that I was doing with Spyder
I think they probably saw my YouTube videos and
amazing
yeah they reach out to me and they were like
do you want do you
do you want to be part of this
they were just starting they
they got a grant
and they were just starting the project
and they kind of just invited me to join
and a lot of the work that I did at the beginning
was actually
writing
guides and doing actually like
videos for beginners to the ecosystem
that's how I joined
That sounds amazing
like I think you showed just like
there are so many ways to contribute to the community
like I think writing documentation and
giving visibility of the project sharing
you know how other people use that IDE
it's very important so
I think it's always something that is so important
but then a lot of people just overlook it right
like sometimes you know
you say like oh
I have created this functionality
people be like wow
and then if you say oh
I write this documentation
people like
ok so I think yeah
it's like
but it's very important
because if nobody is writing any documentation or
or doing all these work
that is less glamorous than no one knew
it's coming to the community
and it become like a project
that everybody have grey hair and you know
nobody
like the young people doesn't care about it anymore
you know that
then the project will probably
be less popular than what it is so
yeah and I
I actually didn't know
that I was gonna end up doing docs
when I joined
I was doing like I was just fixing bugs like any
any like beginner developer in a project
and I ended up like involved with documentation
and I guess my first goal was to make it more friendly
I guess my like first goal was to make it more friendly
so a lot of it was like
literally just putting screenshots and Gifs in the
the documentation which it was a lot of work
I thought it was very important to kinda like
include more people and to make it easier
to learn how to use a tool
especially
cause it wasn't meant for software developers
it was meant for scientists who don't necessarily know
um like all the fundamentals of software development
and I think making
it easier to use by having
very good docs was kind of like one of my first goals
when I hear your story just now
I like how you mention that
trying to reach different audience
different subset of group of
you know
people who consume YouTube
like I think I don't really have YouTube channels
I tried it's not easy to to run it
so I think it's amazing that you're doing that
I'm also not good at that
I tried
I won't be a very good Youtuber
I think I'm just a goofball
I don't know how to do marketing
how to like you know
I kind of analyze what people like
what people don't like I just do what I like
and I don't think it's a very good strategy
funny enough
the reason that I was able to do a lot of the like
to do
editing and like I guess
the creative part of the
tutorials and all of these things was because
I had a YouTube channel that was for music
so I was like
I started like when I was in my undergrad
I started like a music YouTube channel
so I was like recording songs and doing videos
like music videos
and I started a YouTube channel
so I had to learn how to do video editing
and that's kind of why I was able to do this
like it was like just random skills that I picked up
doing something else
that I was able to put into practice
while doing documentation
yeah so you were already like
doing music thing before TikTok become a thing
right now everybody is like dancing
I don't do TikTok though
sometimes see people in the in the square
they were just like you know
young people they play some music
they look very cool and like dancing
and I was like
I'm so old right
I'm not used to TikTok I'll be like
oh that remind me of when I was in uni
like the dance club people
and then my friend who is younger was like
they probably not dance club
they're just doing TikTok
I was like what is that
yeah
and that's what the younger generations are doing now
yeah And I actually I didn't do that for Spyder
but I did some TikToks for the Scientific
Python project
and I was kind of trying to figure out what was
like short enough to put in a TikTok
that was like educational
I guess because I mean
like nowadays
the way that people consume all of these media is like
it's very short if you do something that
it's longer than 1 or two minutes long in TikTok
they're not gonna watch it
so you need to like break it into very small pieces
like it
so I did some like very basic um
videos on things like how to do your first PR
how to review a PR things like that on TikTok
that was fun but it was very hard
I think that's very interesting
we need to find those links
and share with our audiences
we need to watch those those TikToks you made
yeah
I was very skeptical like even a couple of years ago
uh when I was working at Anaconda
my colleague at the time
Sophia she's also very talented
she did all this like oh
data science short form video
I don't know TikTok or YouTube
whatever
like teaching people data science
I was like
does it work'cause like but well
it proves that I was wrong
it works and now I'm like struggling of like
how can we do that
hahaha
yeah I think you just need to go with
you know what's in these days
you have to I I realize I'm also old
like I don't have TikTok account
but I know that's what the younger people do
and if we want the Python committee to stay relevant
maybe we need to start doing this
we need young people
yeah
you know if you ask us to decide on oh
what to do
we just come up with something that maybe work like
10 years ago but not working now
so
but anyway let's go back to what Juanita has been doing
um you also do a lot of security work
which I think again like
is something that is very important and it's like
getting more and more attention these days
for open source so what made you go into the field
like is it because you love open source
you want to do something for it
or is it just like oh
security super cool
I want to do that which come first
so when I started my PhD
I was actually I joined the Security Lab
I wasn't working on open source at first
and the reason I joined the Security Lab was because
my background is actually in
math and I did some cryptography stuff
so my advisor
thought that I would be a good fit to do some like
security
stuff so at the beginning
I was actually doing like cryptography things
not related to open source at all
so I had this like
divided life where like during the day
I was working in security and during the night
I was working in open source
um and I thought that wasn't cool
I thought that
I would be better if I could merge
like my passion and my
research
so
I started talking to people at the Open Source Program
office in my university and I guess they were like
interested in working with me
I had a lot of experience in like
community work
and like a lot of contacts within the ecosystem
so I I think that was that was good
and I think the reason I
decided to kind of bring security into the open source
work that I was doing was because I saw like
a gap
like by talking to maintainers and to developers
I realized that
security is something that people are concerned about
but they're not necessarily experts on
they don't necessarily have the time for
so it's something that it's important
but it's not addressed
like as much as I think it should be
so I think I wanted to bridge that gap
kind of to just kind of help maintainers with security
I am definitely not an expert yet
on
a lot of what the things that I've been doing is like
learning about
what is it that you need in your open source project
I would say be like more secure
and that's where I'm headed
is I want to be able to help maintainers
I want to I want to work on the human part of security
not necessarily like bug bounties or
I don't know like more yeah
I would say like hacky things but more um
learning about best practices and security
and helping maintainers implement those
best practices in their projects
I think that's kind of like my goal
cause I think that would be
a useful contribution to the ecosystem
I always like had this image of like
oh security is super cool
like you know
just like what you said the
you know the bug bounty and stuff is look like
like Wild West like instead of cowboy
you have all these like Sci-Fi hero and things
but then like I think yeah
it's more serious than you know
the fantasy world that you have to really
put your foot down and do a lot of like
very fundamental work that a
lot of people don't see
I just found it very difficult
that's why I kind of
uh left that kind of trend on like doing security
I I'm totally not a very secure person
I jaywalk all the time you know
this is like
not security reasons
yeah
I know you still you mention you're like
you're learning right now
but is there something actionable
we can do as an open source maintainer
to be even more secure right now
so I think um
for example github uh
is one of those places
that has been helping a lot with security practices
and I feel like they've made it easier
for maintainers to implement
some of their
like security stuff in their repositories
I would start with that
I would start with like anything that Github
like recommends they have very concise guides on like
beginner practices I would say
things like implementing secret scanning
or static analysis in your repositories
or like dependency updates
like automatic dependency updates with dependabot
some of these things are things that Github has
I think made very easy for maintainers to implement
so I would start with that
but
another thing that I've been doing a lot with
the repositories
so I'm I'm actually working with
the projects that are associated with the university of
California system
that's kind of the population that I'm working
just because I'm um
working from the OSPO of the university
and with other OSPOs
and a lot of what I'm doing with
these projects is analyzing
everything from like health practices
as in like do they have contributing guides
do they have issue templates
all of these things
all the way to more like advanced security stuff
and
one of the tools that I use a lot is the score cards
from the Open SSF
which is just a tool that will allow you to
measure a bunch of different security flags
in your repositories
I don't necessarily think that the score
is important to tell you
the actual picture of security in your repository
but it will give you some action items
so you will see some of the things that you are lacking
and it will give you some
good action things to start with
to increase the security
or your repository
I would say
maybe those two things would be
uh huh
Things that I'm
Looking into right now
ya
so I'm familiar with the Github
you know
security checklist and I think it's very important
the secret scanning I know in the past
a long time ago I was a newbie
I committed the secret and I'm glad that it caught it
so
but the open SSF
score card how do we get that
I know I've heard this before
but I don't know how it works
like how do you get scored
so there's multiple ways of doing it
I mean if you go to the Scorecard dot Dev website
they just have
like a very easy explanation of how to get it
you can install it as a Github action
in your repository
so it would kind of run automatically
I don't do it like
that because I don't do it for my own repositories
I do it for other repositories
so they also have a CLI
so you just clone the repo
install the package
and you can just run it in your terminal
like scorecard
and then you put the link of the repository
and then it just runs
yeah like
like a CLI and they have like different output formats
so for example
what I do is I collect everything in JSON
and then I kind of
cause I'm running it for multiple repos
so I just have a python script
that will run it for all of them
and then I collect everything in JSON
and I just do a fancy CSV table
so I can see the results
but yeah you can do it as a github action also
oh I didn't know about this
I didn't know there was CLI
we need this run on our repos
should we actually run it on all kinds of repos
or is there certain projects
do you think that maybe more prone to this
should we run it against our PyPodcats website
I mean I don't know I'm
I'm actually also struggling with that
because I think that there is a lot of the checks
that scorecards have that
maybe are not important for
some types of repositories
like if it's like a very beginner repository
then some of the checks might not make as much sense
so I think it is okay to run it in every repository
as long as you can
kind of be objective about knowing what
the metrics that you are looking at mean
and how the characteristics of your repository
like make or not sense with the metrics that you're
looking at I think
it's a very cool tool
just because it will give you some
things that you can improve
regardless of what stage is your repository on
but I
I think it's something to be careful about that it's
it might not be like not all of the checks
might apply
for the type of project that you're working on
okay
now I want to address the elephant in the room like AI
is it good or bad for security in open source
oh my God
I think it could be good
um for certain things
I think AI for everything
it should be used very carefully
and I think understanding what AI is
understanding the way I see is part of life
is part of that it's like understanding that
it's not like a magician that's telling you answers
it's just statistics right
and I think that is part of
maybe the problem when people like
use it too much is like
they don't really know what's behind it
I've actually done a project with like
identifying vulnerabilities in code using AI
and I actually had fairly good results with like
the newest models
so I think there is
a possibility that maybe in the future
AI could be something very good for identifying
like
certain code patterns or
some of these things that could be dangerous
for your repositories
um whether life on that like 100%
I'm not sure like I wouldn't be like
oh I give this to an AI
and then if the AI says this is safe
then it's safe
I don't think that would be the way that I would do it
but I do think it it
could be a very good tool to uncover some things uh
like in an automatic way
now everybody's thinking like
how AI is gonna change our life
our profession and everything
so I have to ask this question
hmm
so Juanita I
I meant you earlier on you talk about
you know you've been
been involved in the community side of open source
you help run
you know hackathon and things
do you have some stories to share
like maybe there are unique events that happened
or are there certain challenges
that you'd like to share with our listeners
um let me think about it
so I think um I've done
like helping organize summits
for the Scientific Python Project
so we we do like a yearly summit with maintainers
this is has been only going for like three years
and I was
I was there for the first summit and it was a very
like a new experience for me to just kind of
figure out what you need to organize an event with like
the community
I think that maybe one of the challenging things from
from this is like how do you make people happy
cause you're like inviting them to uh
be in like a week or just like working on open source
which is already what most of them do
but it's like
they have to travel and they have to like
spend like a lot of their time
and like a lot of
cause it's more like a hands on thing
and I think things like
you need to find where they're gonna have dinner
And you need to find the food and like all of these things
and like all of these things are things that you maybe
you don't imagine that you have to plan
when you're organizing an event
but then it's like
people have to eat and you have to find them a hotel
like on all of these things was definitely challenging
and then I've also
being part of the organizing committee for SciPy
the the conference
and I'm in the like the communication side of it
so I help a lot with the social media outreach
that's kind of
what my main focus has been for the past three years
I've also seen you singing on stage for SciPy
oh yeah
yes
I don't know if we have that recording
yeah there's there's recordings for sure
we have a group that we call SciPy 5
and we make it part of the Lightning talks
so at the end of the conference
the last lightning talk is like a song
so we
we use
different things that have happened
during the conference
and we like create a song with it
wow
And then we just sing a song at the end of the conference
it's hilarious
it's been one of the most fun experiences to do in SciPy
and I think SciPy is one of those conferences where
beautiful places in the world
I've been in other conferences
but I would not do that like
I would not put myself on a stage and sing a song for
like the conference
but SciPy is a very cool conference for that
I haven't been to SciPy so that sounds
that sounds fun
I think we need to bring more of this to other make
let's make other conferences fun as well
I haven't been to PyCon
okay you have to come
come to PyCon yeah
you need to stay on stage for us
You have to sing on stage
cause we have so many like
musical talents in the coredev team as well
I remember they produce a record for the PyLadies auction one year
so maybe you can you know
kind of have a jam session
that would be fun
I would love to go to PyCon
um yeah
I think
you know SciPy and PyCon
you know all these community things great
but I know it's not always
you know sunshine and rainbows
you know
cause Mariatta can resonate right
like in open source you know
there's still like only around 10% of women and like
you know also security
I don't see a lot of women in security
as cyber security either so how do you navigate that
like
like what challenges do you face when like being
you know
a member of the underrepresented group in the industry
yeah
I guess my biggest challenge is the imposter syndrome
of like
feeling that I'm not good enough to be part of like
this community
I guess not necessarily
because I'm in an underrepresented community
but also just because my background is very different
like I didn't come from software
I actually come from math
so I feel like sometimes I lack a lot of these basics
and I also think that this challenge is like
I haven't had that a lot
but there's definitely been some
situations where I feel like I've
I've been treated differently
because I am part of an underrepresented community
I'm both a woman and Latina
so I'm doubly underrepresented
and I think
I think it's it's been tough in some situation
but at the but at the same time
it's make me want to work harder
I mean to prove myself
but also to represent the communities
right
to like to make sure that people know that women are
to make sure that people know that women
can also be great at their jobs
can also be great coders can also be great at
at managing people like all of these things
so I think it's
it's inspire me to work harder
maybe some of that comes from my own
like insecurity and imposter syndrome
but I think the consequences are good
I think the consequences of like
working harder
and trying to achieve more and grow more are
are always good
and I also think that
I mean one of the ways that
I guess I navigate that is by
getting closer to people who will inspire me
and will
I guess elevate my work
and I think the open source community
I think the open source community
the Python community the scientific Python community
it's full of those people
it's full of people who will
tell you all the time how good of a job you're doing
and will elevate you
and will teach you and will mentor you
and I think that's been like
the most important thing for me
is to surround myself
with the people that will allow me to grow
and not
kind of push me down
that's really important and I love hearing this
ya
And I feel like a lot of us can really
relate and resonate with what you
you know what you experience
I do believe that it's
it's very important to find the right
of the right community and I do
I agree like
the Python community is kind of special in that
you can always find someone like
I feel the whole community is always there
wanting and willing to help you and support you so
and I think you mentioned a very good point
like imposter syndrome
because I don't know when I meet you maybe
maybe like you know
a little bit before SciPy or
or SciPy I can't remember
but like
we met in Colombia
Maybe oh maybe PyCon Colombia yes
yeah but when I look at you
it's just like oh my God
you're so amazing so confident and so many talent
and I feel like
even if you say that you have imposter syndrome
I I'm pretty sure that a lot of people in the community
will feel the same you know
like
so sometimes you know
is sometimes you know
um yeah
finding a
supportive group that you can just be open about it
and like you know
that is very
that's that's very valuable
yeah and I feel like for me as well
one of the reasons I feel like
I'm not good enough is because I don't see a lot of
people who look like me you know
people I who I can relate to
and sometimes you feel like you just question yourself
like
am I really really good am I here because I'm good
or am I here just because
they need to feel in somebody
you know
um I
I think that's still a challenge that I
personally face I don't know about you all
yeah no for sure
I always feel like a lot of times
like
we trying to compare things that are not comparable
I've seen a lot of women in tech
they do a lot of very important role
they take on very important role
doing very important work
but maybe they are not always those like shiny and like
you know work that admire by a lot of people
so
it's unfair to compare like
those people's achievement to the more typical
people's achievement and I think that's
you know
sometimes make you feel a bit underwhelmed of your
what you have done so yeah
yeah that's true
and I think when I first joined the Spyder Team I
I was actually the only woman
and that was a lot of responsibility for me
like
I felt like I was representing women in the team and I
I had to kind of put the face of like what
what women can do um
that was a lot of responsibility
but it was
I think it was also a very good experience for me to
like
you know like just learn that I can do all these things
at the beginning
I wasn't a software developer
when I got invited to be part of the Spyder team
and I was like I don't know if I can do this
but just
joining the team
and being part of a community that wants to help you
and mentor you
I think that was
that was a great experience
and it's good that you bring those like
experience and to kind of help other people as well
uh huh
thaat's great yeah
I'd like to hear more about your
you your other YouTube about singing haha
can you tell us more about it
can you have a links to share haha
should we subscribe to it
yes yes
yeah so I
I actually started singing when I was very
very little
like in like maybe choirs and
and bands and stuff like that
and actually when I was like 12 years old
I went to The X Factor in Colombia and um
wow I passed a few rounds then they kicked me out
and I remember one of the judges told me like
you have a very pretty voice
but you need
you need to study cause you don't have enough
like volume and enough like projection of your voice
and that was for me
like that's what made me want to become better
so as like as after I got kicked out of The X Factor
I went and I started studying music and taking like
vocal technique lessons
and I guess I I yeah
I started becoming better and I think after yeah
so when I was in my undergrad I started this project
I created a YouTube channel and I started uh
recording and doing videos
it was always covers
I've never been like writing my own music
but it's it's been always like covers
um but it was like a lot of work
so after maybe two years I was like
I don't think I can do this as much so I
I have a YouTube channel with a lot of videos
but I haven't done much in the past few years
and I also have played with like different bands
so before I
I moved from Colombia to the US like four or five
years ago and before I moved I was uh
singing with a band and we had some like
concerts and things like that
and that was very very fun
and now I'm in the US and it's a little bit harder
and I
I not necessarily have found the right people haha
to do music
but it's something that I definitely still have in me
like I think music is one of those things that I
I never leave behind and
the first thing I bought when I got here was a guitar
and then I bought a piano
a keyboard it's right there
oh
yeah
and it's like one of those things that I feel
feels my heart with joy so it's
I guess it keeps my mental health
and
it's something that I like to share a lot with people
too
so just like singing for people
playing for people is something that I really
I really enjoy doing too
I have to break a news for you
cause this year in Europython
they have formed a band
so
oh wow
yes it started with
you know I don't know if you know him
our friend Moses like he perform a little bit of like
you know a music at
at the lighting talk just like you do
you know it's just a little bit fun music
and then it grow and grow into like
there are more and more people joining him
and they will bring their musical
instrument to EuroPython and this year
if you look at the recording
like they perform all together on stage
that's amazing so
um just so you know
you can come to EuroPython and jam with everyone
they would love to have you
I would love to do that
I think it's uh
for me I'm just
I really admire that like I
I admire your you know
like rejection not rejection
like you got kicked out
you mentioned you got kicked out from something
but you took it as motivation to make you even better
I think that's really inspiring
like congrats for doing that
some people thinks like once they fail at something
they give up they don't wanna do it anymore
but you continued on to do it so it's really cool
when I was a kid I wanted to be Shakira
to be what
Shakira
oh yes I love her music
yes yes yes
I was like is everybody in Colombia so talented
I think so
yeah
I wanted to be her when I was a kid
I thought I was gonna like
follow that path and study music
and just become a musician
like be a singer
I'm glad I didn't
because I think that I would have missed
on all the other side of
the work that I do and the things that I do
that are also very close to my heart
but I yeah
it's funny cause I
I really thought that that's what I was gonna do
yeah I do enjoy going to
dancing with the organisers of PyCon Colombia
that's
that's amazing I was like
I won't struggle cause a lot of times we say like
oh like if you go to PyCon or like
we are just a bunch of nerds
we don't party we don't dance
no look at that I mean like
mm hmm mm hmm
everybody dance  we're cool nerds
hahaha yes hahaha
we also dance a little bit
like at the social event of PyCon Greece
I think at the end
usually it's like people need to really like
you know
warm up
spend lots of time to warm up until they will be like
okay now we can dance
but like I like in
in Colombia
it's just like everybody just like right away
you know let's dance
you know like
we're very warm
that's just yeah
another thing that I I really miss
I have
I really miss PyCon Colombia that that was really
really fun experience that was
I miss the community there
they are just amazing yeah
oh yeah
or do you have any other topics we want
you want to talk about before we wrap it up
um no
I would say thank you so much for inviting me
and I really feel very grateful to be part of um
the Python community the
the Python community the scientific Python community
the open source community in general
and
I really love the work that you two are doing
in elevating the people from the community
and showing the work that they're doing um
to the world
cause I think that is a very important part of
of being part of of this
you know of
of feeling that the work that you're doing counts
and that people um
appreciate it
so I'm really grateful that you invited me and
and yeah I hope you keep up the
the good work cause I'm I'm really yeah
I really like what you're trying to do
thank you Juanita
thank you for joining us we're really grateful to hear
and I think your story is really inspiring
so yeah thank you so much
yeah so thank you so much for inspiring all of us
if you who are watching
if you want us to inspire more people
please uh
consider donating to PyPodcats
uh because
you know to produce this kind of
episode uh
it's not like running a conference
it's not as expensive
but it still require money to have all this equipment
we are not monetizing our videos or podcast
so we need your uh donation to support us to
we need your uh donation to support us
you know
keep doing this and inspire more people and um
just
give people who have been
people who have
doing so much hard work for the community a shout out
so people know about them
thank you so much for watching
and this is Juanita amazing
thank you
hope to see you
again next time in our next episode of PyPodcats
Hidden Figures of Python
thank you everybody bye
people really have a lot of fun with that